Preservation League of New York State; Records apap134
State University of New York at Albany, also known as SUNY Albany
Preservation League of New York State Records
1975-2002
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Preservation League of New York State
apap134
1.0 cubic ft.
This collection contains the Preservation League of New York State’s official newsletters, annual reports, materials for and from its annual awards ceremony, correspondence, various publications and manuals created by its members, grant materials, directories of members and preservation programs and organizations, and a timeline of the Preservation League’s history ranging from 1975-2002.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Michele Patterson, an employee of the Preservation League of New York State, donated the records to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives in 2002.
Historical Note
The Preservation League of New York State was established in Rensselaerville, New York in June 1973 when a group of preservationists gathered together to focus on a need for an organization whose mission would be to promote the ethics and tools of preservation while providing assistance throughout the state and helping to shape federal, state, and local policies. During the last four decades, the Preservation League has educated New Yorkers through the dissemination of its publications and creation of a variety of seminars, presentations, and workshops on the resources available to help protect, maintain, and restore properties.
The Preservation League is still active today.
Scope and Contents
The Preservation League of New York State’s records begin with its first newsletter in 1975 and contains newsletters and other publications from 1975-2002 along with other materials from that time-frame. This includes annual reports, materials for and from its annual awards ceremony, correspondence, various publications and manuals created by its members, grant materials, directories of members and preservation programs and organizations, and a timeline of the Preservation League’s history ranging from 1975-2002.
The Preservation League’s newsletter changes titles at various points beginning with Newsletter (1975-1993), Preservation New York (1993-1997), News (1997-2000), and ending with New York Preservation (2001-2002). Under the Preservation New York title, Vol. 13, No. 1 is missing from the collection.
Separated Materials
The archivist transferred one monograph: The National Register of Historic Places in New York State compiled for the Preservation League of New York State by Peter D. Shaver to the book division of Special Collections. It was catalogued and included in Minerva, the University Library Catalog.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized alphabetically. There are no series.
Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Architecture--Conservation and restoration--New York (State); Historic preservation--New York (State); Historic buildings--conservation and restoration--New York (State); Reports; Serial (publications); Gill, Brendan, 1914-1997; Preservation League of New York State
- Access & Authenticity…Historic Library Buildings Resolving Physical Access & Historic Preservation Issues in Public Library Buildings, Undated (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 1)
- Among the Survivors, 1990 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 2)
- Annual Report, 1990-1995 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 3)
- Annual Report, Preservation League of New York State Annual Report and Awards, 1996-1998; 2000-2001 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 4)
- Annual Report, 2001 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 5)
- Awards Materials, 1984 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 6)
- Awards Materials, 1985 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 7)
- Awards Materials, Historic Civic Building Award Conferred to Governor Mario M. Cuomo, 1985 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 8)
- Awards Materials, 1986 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 9)
- Awards Materials, 1988 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 10)
- Awards Materials, 1989 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 11)
- Awards Materials, 1990 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 12)
- Awards Materials, 1991 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 13)
- Awards Materials, 1992 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 14)
- Awards Materials, 1993 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 15)
- Awards Materials, 1995 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 16)
- Awards Materials, 1996 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 17)
- Awards Materials, 1997 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 18)
- Awards Materials, 1998 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 19)
- Awards Materials, 1999 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 20)
- Awards Materials, 2000 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 21)
- Awards Materials, 2001 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 22)
- Awards Materials, 2002 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 23)
- Commission Partners Training Manual, 2000 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 24)
- Correspondence, 1981; 1985 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 25)
- Correspondence to Darlene McCloud (President of Preservation League of New York State), 1999 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 26)
- A Fair Land to Build In: The Architecture of the Empire State, 1984 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 27)
- Farmsteads and Market Towns: A Handbook for Preserving the Cultural Landscape, 1982 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 28)
- Good Buildings Good Times: A Manual of Program Ideas for Promoting Local Architecture, 1985 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 29)
- Grant Materials, 2002; Undated (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 30)
- How to Care for Religious Properties, 1982 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 31)
- New York: Profiting Through Preservation, 2000 (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 32)
- New York State Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation -- Historic Preservation Field Services Bureau, Undated (Box 1 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 33)
- Newsletter (Preservation League of New York State), 1975-1981 (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 1)
- Newsletter (Preservation League of New York State), 1982-1988 (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 2)
- Newsletter (Preservation League of New York State), 1989-1993 (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 3)
- Newsletter Correspondents, 1980 (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 4)
- New York Preservation, 2001-2002 (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 5)
- News (Preservation League of New York State), 1997-2000 (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 6)
- Preservation New York, 1993-1997 (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 7)
- Preservation: Building Community Identity, 1981 (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 8)
- Preservation Calendar & Statewide Preservation News, 1988-1992 (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 9)
- Preservation Colleague’s Directory, 2001 (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 10)
- Preservation Directory: A Guide to Programs, Organizations, and Agencies in New York State, 1988 (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 11)
- Preservation for Profit: Ten Case Studies in Commercial Rehabilitation, 1980 (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 12)
- Preservation League of New York State 1984-1998 Award Winners, Undated (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 13)
- Preservation League of New York State Reprint Series, 1978 (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 14)
- Preservation League of New York State Resources Series, 1976-1977 (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 15)
- Preservation League of New York State Technical Series, 1976; 1982; Undated (Box 2 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 16)
- The Preservation League of New York State: Twenty-Five Years of Preserving New York State, 1974-1999, Undated (Box 3 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 1)
- Preserving the Past and Making It Accessible for People with Disabilities, 1992 (Box 3 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 2)
- A Primer: Preservation for the Property Owner, 1978 (Box 3 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 3)
- Timeline – Preservation League of New York State, 25th Annual Report, Undated (Box 3 (Preservation League of New York State Records), Folder 4)